Wilted spinach salad

This salad has been on the menu since the restaurant opened and is still a favourite we make every day. The spinach is tossed with very hot olive oil, which cooks it slightly, sweetening and softening the leaves. As the feta cheese and the olives are both salty, no additional salt is needed.

Makes 2 large or 4-6 small salads

Ingredients

red onion 1 small, quartered and thinly sliced

Baguette 3 to 4 slices per person, for croutons

olive oil 6 tbsp

kalamata olives 8 to 12

spinach 450g

garlic 1 clove, finely chopped

(mint leaves 1 tbsp, finely chopped)

sherry vinegar 2 tbsp

Feta cheese 175g

Preparation

Preheat the oven to 180C fan/gas mark 6. Cover the onion slices with cold water and refrigerate until needed. Brush the bread with some of the olive oil and toast it in the oven until it is crisp and lightly browned, 6 to 8 minutes.

Press the olives to split them open, take out the stones, and cut or tear the olives in two. Remove the spinach stems (or not, as you prefer) and discard any bruised or yellow leaves. Cut the large leaves into halves or thirds; small leaves can be left whole.

Wash the spinach, using two changes of water if the spinach is very sandy, and spin dry.

When you are ready to make the salad, drain the onions. Put the spinach in a large metal bowl and toss it with the onions, garlic, mint, olives and vinegar. Break up the cheese and crumble it over the spinach.

Heat the rest of the olive oil until it is very hot but just short of smoking. Immediately pour it over the salad,turning the leaves with a pair of metal tongs so that the hot oil coats and wilts as many leaves as possible. Taste, and season with more vinegar if needed. Serve the salad with the croutons tucked in and around the leaves.

This salad could be accompanied with a moderately dry riesling, or perhaps a zinfandel or beaujolais.

Variations: instead of using only spinach, combine it with curly endive, escarole or thinly sliced red cabbage – all leaves that respond well to being prepared in this way.

Chocolate Chip Cookies (Reconstructed)

When I was a kid, we used to make Toll House Cookies, but with a variation of the recipe that was then on the back of each package of Toll House chocolate chips. I was never able to find that recipe, but this is a close reconstruction.

3 cups all-purpose flour

1 teaspoon baking soda with 1 teaspoon warm water

1 teaspoon salt

1 1/2 sticks of butter, softened

3/4 cups granulated (white) sugar

3/4 cups brown sugar, packed

1 teaspoon vanilla extract

2 eggs

1 cup semi-sweet chocolate chips (when I was a kid, we used Nestle's, but I've recently tried Ghirardelli; I think 3/4 cups may be sufficient

1 cup chopped walnuts

Preheat oven to 375°F.

Combine softened butter, sugars, salt, and vanilla in bowl. Stir until creamy. Add the baking soda solution near the end of the stirring (I've never been sure why it is a solution?).

Add the eggs, and stir until mixed.

Now layer a cup of flour, sifted; the chocolate; another cup of flour, sifted; the nuts; and the last cup of flour. Stir all this until you can't see the flour any more.

Get a bunch on a teaspoon and drop onto un-greased baking sheets. And by teaspoon, I mean a big heaping teaspoon – the goal is to make big thick cookies – thicker than any normal chocolate chip cookie you've had in the past. I could get about 15 on the large cookie sheet and 12 on the smaller insulated sheet.

Bake 14-16 minutes on the un-insulated sheet on the middle shelf, and 2 minutes longer for the insulated sheet on the lower shelf. The goal here is to get them brown all over and on the bottom, and have them look cake-like and not moist when you break them in half.

Vegan Bulgogi (The Guardian 5-8-21)

Ingredients

280g extra-ﬁrm tofu

4 tbsp light soy sauce

1½ tbsp brown rice syrup

5 garlic cloves, peeled and crushed

3cm piece fresh ginger, peeled and grated

1 pear, coarsely grated

10 spring(green) onions, trimmed and sliced, whites and greens separated

4 tbsp toasted sesame oil

1 tbsp gochujang paste

4 tbsp rapeseed (or olive or grapeseed) oil

400g (chestnut, or white, or portabello, or crimini) mushrooms, sliced

Cooked jasmine rice, to serve

Preparation:

Lightly press the tofu block between your hands over the sink, to get rid of as much water as possible, then wrap in paper towels and set aside.

Put the soy sauce, brown rice syrup, garlic, ginger, pear, spring onion whites, sesame oil, gochujang and two tablespoons of water in a bowl and whisk to mix. Unwrap the tofu from the kitchen paper and cut widthways into ¾cm-thick slices.

Heat up two tablespoons of the rapeseed oil in a large frying pan over a medium heat, and have ready a large plate by the side of the cooker. Fry the mushrooms in batches, so that each slice can touch the base of the pan (otherwise they’ll sweat, rather than fry), until they turn golden – each batch should take about five minutes – then transfer to the plate and repeat with the remaining mushrooms.

Coat the bottom of the pan with the remaining rapeseed oil, then fry the tofu for about four minutes, turning once, until golden on both sides. Tip the mushrooms back into the pan, stir in the soy and gochujang, and cook for five minutes, until the sauce has reduced and coated everything.

Sprinkle over the chopped spring onion greens and serve with rice.

Broccoli and Cauliflower Gratin

Ingredients

4 tbsp. (1/2 stick) unsalted butter, plus more for pan

1 medium head cauliflower (about 2 pounds), cored and sliced 1/4-inch thick

1 large head broccoli (about 1 1/2 pounds), trimmed and sliced 1/4-inch thick

6 tbsp. all-purpose flour

3 c. whole milk

1/4 tsp. freshly grated nutmeg

8 oz. Gruyère, grated (about 2 cups)

Kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper

Instructions

Preheat oven to 375°F. Butter a shallow 3-quart baking dish. Arrange cauliflower and broccoli in the prepared dish.

Melt butter in a medium saucepan over medium heat. Add flour and cook, stirring, 2 minutes (do not let it darken). Slowly whisk in milk.

Simmer, whisking occasionally, until slightly thickened, 3 to 4 minutes. Remove from heat and stir in nutmeg and 1 1/4 cups cheese. Season with salt and pepper. Pour over vegetables. Sprinkle with remaining 3/4 cup cheese.

Cover loosely with aluminum foil and bake for 15 minutes. Remove foil; bake until vegetables are tender and the top is golden brown, 20 to 25 minutes. Let stand 10 minutes before serving.

Crab and Spinach Quiche

Ingredients:

1/2 package pie crust mix (or your own pie crust recipe)

1 package (10 ounces) frozen chopped spinach

2 eggs, lightly beaten

8 ounces plain yogurt

1 tablespoon flour

1/4 teaspoon salt

Freshly ground black pepper

1 can (6 1/2 ounces) crabmeat, well drained and picked over to remove shell fragments

1 can (4 1/2 ounces sliced mushrooms, drained

1 cup shredded Cheddar cheese (4 ounces)

1 small onion, finely minced (1/4 cup)

Preparation:

Preheat oven to 425. Prepare the pie crust according to recipe or instructions for a 9 inch pie pan.

Bake pie crust in oven for 5 minutes or until set. Remove from oven and place on wire rack.

Cook spinach according to label instructions; drain, squeezing out excess water.

Beat the eggs with yogurt, flour, salt, and pepper in medium size bowl. Stir in the spinach and crabmeat.

Sprinkle the onion, mushrooms and cheese on the pie crust. Pour in the spinach mixture.

Bake in hot oven (425 degrees) for 15 minutes. Then lower heat to 350 degrees and bake for another 30 minutes or until a knife inserted in the middle comes out clean.

King Arthur Baking Company

Sunken Berry Almond Cake

PREP 10 mins -BAKE 35 to 40 mins

YIELD one 8“ cake

Ingredients

2 cups (192g) King Arthur Almond Flour

2 tablespoons (14g) cornstarch

2 teaspoons baking powder

1/4 teaspoon table salt

6 tablespoons (85g) unsalted butter, at room temperature, plus more for greasing the pan

1/2 cup plus 2 tablespoons (124g) granulated sugar, divided

zest of 1/2 lemon

4 large eggs, separated

1 teaspoon King Arthur Pure Vanilla Extract

1/4 teaspoon almond extract

3/4 to 1 cup (105g to 150g) blueberries, raspberries, or blackberries*

King Arthur Snow White Non-Melting Sugar or confectioners' sugar, for dusting

*Cut any large berries in half.

Instructions

Preheat the oven to 350°F.

Lightly grease an 8” round cake pan or line with a parchment round. Grease the parchment and sides of the pan to ensure the cake releases easily.

In a medium bowl, whisk together the almond flour, cornstarch, baking powder, and salt.

In another medium bowl or the bowl of your stand mixer, beat the butter, 1/2 cup (99g) of the sugar, and the lemon zest until fluffy and well combined, about 4 to 5 minutes. Add the egg yolks and extracts and beat until well combined, about 30 seconds.

Add the almond flour mixture to butter mixture and beat until just combined.

In a clean bowl with clean beaters, beat the egg whites and the remaining 2 tablespoons (25g) sugar to soft peaks, about 3 minutes.

Mix about 1/2 cup of the beaten egg whites into the almond flour mixture to loosen it. Then gently fold the remaining egg whites into the almond flour mixture, being careful not to deflate the egg whites (some lingering streaks are OK).

Transfer the batter to the prepared pan and smooth the top. Place the berries on top of the batter, spacing them evenly around the outer 3“ of the pan. (As the cake bakes, the batter pushes the berries toward the middle. Starting with the berries around the edge of the pan will result in a more even distribution in the end.) There's no need to push the berries into the batter; they'll sink as the cake bakes.

Bake the cake for about 35 to 40 minutes, until golden brown and a toothpick or thin knife inserted into the center comes out with moist crumbs attached (rather than batter).

Let the cake cool in the pan on a wire rack for 10 minutes. Carefully flip the cake out of the pan, invert it onto a rack so that it’s right-side up, and let it cool completely. Dust with non-melting sugar or confectioners’ sugar before serving.

Store the almond flour cake, well-wrapped at room temperature, for several days.

Tips from our Bakers For a plainer almond flour cake that you can top with whipped cream and fresh fruit or frost as a birthday cake, omit the lemon and berries.

One-Pan Coconut Milk-Braised Chicken

Yield: Serves 4 Prep Time: 20 minutes Cook Time: 25 minutes to 30 minutes

Ingredients

2 cloves garlic

1 (3-inch) piece fresh ginger

2 pounds bone-in, skin-on chicken thighs (4 to 6)

1 1/2 teaspoons kosher salt, divided

2 tablespoons canola oil, divided

3 tablespoons Thai green curry paste

1 (13 to 14-ounce) can full-fat coconut milk

For garnish: *

1/2 bunch fresh cilantro,1/2 small red onion,1 small jalapeño pepper

1 medium lime

Instructions

Arrange a rack in the middle of the oven and heat the oven to 350°F.

Mince 2 garlic cloves, then peel and finely chop 1 (3-inch) piece fresh ginger (about 2 tablespoons). Pat 2 pounds bone-in, skin-on chicken thighs dry with paper towels, then season all over with 1 teaspoon of the kosher salt.

Heat 1 tablespoon of the canola oil in 10-inch cast iron or oven-safe skillet over medium-high until shimmering. Working in batches if needed, add the chicken skin-side down and cook until the fat is rendered and the skin is golden-brown, 7 to 8 minutes. Transfer the chicken to a plate. Pour out the rendered fat and let the pan cool for 5 minutes.

Place the pan back over medium heat. Add the remaining 1 tablespoon canola oil, garlic, and ginger, and cook until fragrant, 3 to 4 minutes. Add 3 tablespoons green curry paste and cook, stirring frequently, until slightly darkened in color and aromatic, 3 to 4 minutes. Add 1 can coconut milk and the remaining 1/2 teaspoon kosher salt, stir to incorporate, and bring to a simmer. Continue to simmer until the curry paste is completely dissolved, 3 to 5 minutes.

Return the chicken to the pan skin-side up in a single layer. Bake uncovered until the sauce is bubbling and an instant-read thermometer registers 165°F in the thickest piece of chicken, 25 to 30 minutes.

Meanwhile, prep the garnishes: coarsely chop 1/2 bunch fresh cilantro, thinly slice 1/2 small red onion and 1 small jalapeño, and cut 1 lime into wedges.

Garnish the chicken with the cilantro, red onion, and jalapeño. Serve with the sauce spooned over chicken and lime wedges for squeezing.

Recipe Notes Storage: Leftovers can be refrigerated in an airtight container up to 2 days.

Curry paste: Curry paste can be found in the international section of most well-stocked grocery stores in cans or small glass jars.